So we will continue looking at the reinforcement
the full reinforcement learning problem so
we left off where we defined a Markov addition
process right and so today's class will probably
be a short one okay because the next thing
next topic I need to start requires me to
define a lot of rotations and stuff like that
so if I start that today I will probably end
up just defining the notation today and then
when I start again next week I will ask you
to I will have to ask you to recall the notation
and stuff like that or spend time writing
it out again so I will not do it.
So if I finish whatever I want to before the
proofs start right I will just stop today
so I will not start the notations okay so
let us see how it goes so right.
.
So we started looking at Markov addition process
plastic so we said that it is specified by
set of states actions right transition probabilities
and right and possibly a ? so if you look
at the RL textbook right they leave out the
? right if you look at any OR textbook were
also mdps are used widely right they would
have the ? in there right so for them g is
a very inherent part of the problem but in
the end the RL books you would see that they
would leave out the ? even though I mean gamma
is inherent part of the problem and somehow
they just do not acknowledge the fact that
gamma changes the solution right licit Lee
in the problem definition itself so this is
essentially what an MDP is all about so what
I will do is walk through one of the examples
from the textbook right.
So I mean sticking is a textbook example so
you can go back and read the book and also
because it is kind of makes the course more
related to the minor guys here okay, so let
us take the example of a recycling robot from
the book so how many of you have been reading
the book okay the number went up by two since
last time okay good Saudi remember the recycling
robot so what was the thing about who is in
any searches for the Cal State is where it
wait for some someone to come and take an
action between these three state based on
the battery level reference ah based on that
they will be reversed whenever it is where
does one will be even okay.
Now it runs out of battery otherwise hmm okay
so it is interesting they just turn on the
mice or something an interesting that you
used the description states okay so people
heard it and if I will repeat it since I seem
to have the Lord Mike so you know that those
can also pick up but I seem to have the Lord
of Mike so let me repeat it so that is this
robot okay that has been created for the express
purpose of switch b hearth okay so it goes
around the building and finds all the empty
cans and gathers it and puts it in some kind
of a no trash recovery system recycling system
or whatever.
So for every can the bot gathers is going
to get a reward of 1 right this is a number
I am pulling out of the Hat right so let us
not talk about the reward in all right so
the robot is supposed to gather Kemp's that
is essentially what we wanted to do but being
a robot it is going to have a limited amount
of power that it can spend right it has a
limited amount of battery power that it can
spend so it has to choose carefully how it
spends the battery right it can go around
looking for cans right and if it is going
to run out of battery then it can do one of
two things it can recharge itself right.
Or it can to sit in a place like a trash can
and expect people to drop the empty cans into
that but okay just kiss sits in a place and
the people can just use it like a trash can
right so this is essentially the set up so
I have this but that should I would like you
to go actively gather cans but I also do not
like it to run out of battery because if it
runs out of battery somebody has to go physically
either roll the robot or carry the lift the
robot and take it to a charging station and
charge it ok that is a very painful operation
so I really do not want it to run out of battery.
But then I do not want it to just sit idle
action as well because what it says is supposed
to do is gather camps right so how would you
model this problem so what are the states
and what are the actions what should be the
reward robot seems to be easy right so well
what you wanted to do you wanted to gather
Ken so whenever it gathers can whenever gather
sir can you give it are ward right so never
gather second to give it a reward of +1 right
so I am going to call this our can +1 right
then what you do not want it to do you do
not want it to run out of battery.
So yes it is just yeah something large right
so yeah so I would I would prefer to give
it -10 or something but since I am walking
through the example in the book okay so it
is a - 3 right so it is not that bad I mean
if we can collect 15 cans and then die is
okay right so it is not too it is not that
bad thing so what else if it charges if it
chooses to charge right so what happens do
we give you what do we do for it is thing
isn't even a positive reward or why does no
reward make sense he'll give yeah just the
heck for pick up getting that reward will
get recharged right but then recharging is
also good we want to convey the fact that
recharging also good.
So it is better than running out of battery
and if you recharge you have the potential
for getting more rewards in the future because
you go out and seek more cans right so that
way you have an indirect incentive for recharging
because in the future it allows you to do
something better if you just look at the immediate
reward it looks like a bad thing but if you
think about it so in the future you are making
it more attractive for recharge I mean if
you look at the future outcomes recharging
is also very attractive okay.
What is below are so many do if they were
charged no this is not this is if you think
about it this is more to do with actions or
something with outcomes yeah battery levels
you could you could make it all the more detail
you can make it as detailed as you want right
now comes the crux how detailed do you want
to make the representation to be do you want
to make it a real number saying how much battery
charge I have you could get a continuous state
there right so what do you want to do you
want to do some kind of dis cartelization
right so if I want to do a dis cartelization
so how do I discredited ah that resistant
question are completely we forgot answers
that question what is the state?
The battery charge level should be the stay
right and then anything else the number of
cans no let us just assume that magically
it takes a can and transports it to well as
an interesting if it has a finite carrying
capacity then you probably need to throw in
how many cans it has and so before it has
to make it trip to the dump dumping ground
or something like that so let us assume for
the time being it so as soon as you put a
can into that there is a teleported that takes
it to the dumping ground okay.
Or the bot has an infinite carry I am just
trying to make the problem simpler right if
you want to make the problem more and more
realistic right you have to think about a
whole bunch of other things right for example
I am kind of making it at a very high level
I am not talking about the person I mean the
post of the robot let the velocity which the
bot is moving so all of these things you need
right if you want to actually going to control
the one and then this assuming all of those
are somehow going to be magically taken care
of right.
So we are just assuming that you are only
worried about the charge of the bot right
yeah we have been talking about only discrete
States in discrete action so far we have not
talked about continuous States and continues
actions but you have continuous state contraction
place okay, so the state is going to be the
charge right and possibly number of cans right
other things but for the time being I am just
going to say I am not going to care about
all of that we will just look at charges to
keep it a simple example right.
I am also keeping it in sync with the book
so and again so what do I do with charge I
can treat it as a number in which case I will
have to figure out how to handle the continuous
value right all I can start discrediting it
so how will I discredited it yeah so I again
well percentage is also not a dis cartelization
unless you round it off okay.
So yeah so you could do something like that
or it could be even more aggressive right
I could do low medium high right and if you
really stop and think about it when would
you if I said if I do low medium high or something
like that whenever I actually change my decision
about charging versus not charging only when
I low okay so in some sense you could even
try operating with high and low and or sufficient
and low okay.
Or whatever is it build is also probably actually
I do not I am not having the location at all
give it so assuming that there is always a
convenient charging point located nearby okay
just not like that a single base station I
have to go there so as soon as I find out
okay I am running out of search and let us
assume that as long as the battery is low
I can still get to a charging point in fact
I am going to assume you in something stronger
so I could with some probability keep operating
even if my battery is low right.
And I still not run out of assumption I make
is the following whenever I say recharge okay
I will have enough battery power to reach
the nearest recharge station and recharge
so after I pick the option to reach other
I will not run out of battery power is again
very simplifying assumption right this makes
it easier for us to draw pictures as I will
in a minute right but all the points that
are being raised to our very good points right
so when you start trying to model a real system
right this is all calls that you will have
to make right.
So what I say that I would throw into my state
right what I say that I can ignore right and
so on so forth and yeah so Paulo we do you
remember the homework assignment we are asking
them yeah the third one we are asking them
we are giving them a word problem when asking
him to construct an MDP out of it right you
think so you were saying Methodism yeah the
one that was released today morning yeah press
release yesterday then your time traveling
okay released this morning.
Yeah so the new assignment and it is due on
feb14 yes 14th is what name Sunday yeah well
plan ahead if it is important to you finish
on the 13th or as it is more likely for lot
of people who have nothing to do 14th only
have a whole last question is that right so
there is a word problem you expect you to
correct MDP, so you can think of similar things
but that is a more constrained word problem
so you will see that there is not too many
ways in which you can construct an MDP out
of it.
So but then the idea is that a lot of design
choices that you make when they give you a
problem specification that the Lord of choices
that you make when you go from the problem
specification to an MDP right so when you
are talking about designing a reinforcement
learning solution for a problem the things
that you have to decide are the states the
actions and the rewards these are the three
things that you have to decide and when you
are constructing an MDP additionally you will
have to figure out what this the transition
probabilities are also going to be because
we thought that you cannot solve the problem.
All right but in we are trying to use reinforcement
learning techniques to solve these problems
as we will see later on you do not need the
transition dynamics I do not need to explicitly
model the transition dynamics but you still
need to make choices for states actions and
towards so that is where we are right now
so after we finish this I will tell you some
simple way of consulting the transition probability
for the robot but that is fine so essentially
what I am going to do charge this is going
to be now low or high okay.
And then what about actions there is no pick
up let us say when I actively we find that
can I will automatically pick it up okay so
I will go so explore essentially or as they
say in the book actively seek cans
because explore is overloaded right so we
have explore exploit those kinds of things
already so I do not want to have an action
called explore okay, so you have you actively
seek cans or wait for cans of recharge right
so there anything else that we need to define
here
yeah so I will tell you how we can get around
the day that is a good point so maybe you
need a zero charge state.
But I also tell you how to get around that
right so the Assumption we are going to make
is if you run out of charge somebody is going
to take you and charge you right then you
are going to get this penalty of minus three
so what does that mean so from low I can actually
go to high with a penalty of minus three ok
so that is that is equivalent to the zero
charge state that you can make it more complex
so right, now I am assuming once you plug
it in to charge I do not worry about it until
fully charged later right see this is another
thing which you with an interesting point
because I have discredited it low and high
right.
So when will it run out of charge when it
when it will go from high to low state so
if I is one 100% high right it is probably
not going to go to the low state when it take
an action but if I say 40% high almost surely
as soon as I take an action it is going to
go into a low state let us say 40 is the way
cutoff point all right so above 40 I say hi
below 40 I say low let us percentage is right
for 40% I will say hi below 40% I will say
low, almost surely as soon as I take an action
it is going to go too low.
But then I am not making this distinction
I have made a dis cartelization here right
so what will it look like to me and if I run
the robot multiple times what will it look
like to me sometimes it goes from high to
low sometimes it goes does not go from high
to low it stays in high so what is going to
happen here is I am going to translate this
into the probabilities of transition right
so what is the probability of going from high
to low in fact if I you know if I knew all
about my the battery dynamics if I know how
much power each and every action takes and
if I modeling this is a continuous valued
state there might not be any causticity here.
But I might be able to tell you very exactly
okay now at this point if this is the action
you are doing this is so much power that you
will consume and therefore the battery will
go from high to low all right so I might be
able to give that to you exactly so inherently
this might not be a stochastic system I am
only saying might not be because people have
worked with robots so you know that he met
he would specify as many initial conditions
as you want right the bots will do what it
wants to do right.
So it is still be a stochastic system but
it could potentially not be a stochastic system
if you know everything about the world right
but we are making it stochastic by virtue
of ignoring certain things that we could potentially
know about the system right and ignoring this
makes the system design a lot simpler maybe
we are giving up some things in terms of how
optimal or solutions can be but that is a
trade-off that you will often have to make
right so just the formulation itself is not
an easy task way to think about it a lot to
figure out toward it be the right place to
draw the line okay.
So these are the actions that we have to take
so I can actively seek can is wait for ken's
recharge is that something else that we have
to specify so I specified the stage they specify
the actions we specified rewards for events
right so if I collector can I get a plus one
right if I run out of battery you get a minus
three then if a recharge you get is you these
are events that could happen in the world
right so these are so I have to relate this
to the states and actions only then I can
tell you what is the expected reward.
I will not talk about time at all right so
I told you for that at least for the initial
part of the course will not talk about time
with how long it run say so what is it that
we need suppose I am actively seeking cans
what is the probability I will get a reward
of +1 if I am actively seeking cans right
what is the probability that I will find a
can correct it is I need to still specify
that if I am actively you are if I am waiting
for cans to come like what is the probability
that I will get a can what is the derivative
of what rid of which one?
Yeah yeah was it Oh y-yeah maybe may be not
I do not know why you chose to move from one
to the other night I mean I could have just
stopped seeking because of his running low
on battery right so if I five min some facility
where people are just taking cancer and throwing
them the dustbin that I am a just happily
go sit next to the can dispensing place and
hacked us at the spin rate I will be happily
getting rewards but I might not even worry
about recharging or anything right.
So I might just choose to stop right so it
depends on that depends on the kind of environment
you are operating in right so even if I act
as a dustbin if do I get enough can send I
might not want to seek right so maybe there
is some time of the day maybe between 12and
1 30 or something lot of cancel come if I
just go stand outside the cafeteria I do not
have to actively seek Ken's maybe after one
30 I have to go around seeking cans and I
do not know it depends on the system it.
I am not trying to be too overly realistic
here but I am just giving you what are the
factors that you have to take into account
right so if you start talking about what could
be optimal policies right then you are going
down a dangerous path that means you are going
to start designing your problem itself depending
on what you think the solution should be which
is a bad thing right you should put in all
the factors about the problem in the design
and then you should go and let the algorithm
figure out what the solution should be.
So you should not start thinking about what
the solution should be and then try to create
the rewards and the model itself I will give
you an example of that after I finish this
I will give an example of when that became
a problem okay so is it clear so now I need
to figure out if I actively seek ends what
is the probability that I will get cancer
right is there anything else I need to know
yeah we will come to that.
Now it is related to that if I am actively
seeking cans what is the probability that
I will run out of battery because that also
determines my reward right or if I am waiting
for Kansas to come what is the probability
I will run out of battery may be 0 because
I have turned off everything and just waiting
for or maybe there is a leakage that is happening
yes a very small probability that I might
actually run out of battery right so.
So I need both of these to actually figure
out what will be the expected reward right
for a state action path.
So I need to know what will be the expected
or what so I have to actually think about
both of these things if I am in a high state
that a time actively seeking cans right so
what is the probability I will find a can
does it depend on whether I am in a high state
or not no right so if I am actively seeking
Ken's what is the probability I will get that
can okay so that is one thing I need likewise
if I am not actively seeking Ken's what is
the probability I will get a can that is second
thing you need on the other hand if I am in
a high state and actively seeking cans.
What is the probability I will run out of
battery there are the state matters right
and likewise if I am in a low state and actively
seeking cans what is the probability I run
out of battery that state matters likewise
for waiting for can see if I am in a high
state and I am waiting for a can yeah probably
of me running out of batteries very very minuscule
almost you know but I can low state and I
am waiting for a can so even with the leakage
power drawn I met actually run out of battery
so these are the things so you need to know
all of these right.
The time being I will say a as the let the
probability of you getting a can write and
ß is the probability of you getting a can
if you are waiting and then a > ß hopefully
typically we were talking about probabilities
I mean that might be momentarily where ß
is higher than a like I said stand outside
the cafeteria during lunch time but then overall
we are going to assume that a >ß since we
have not actually modeled that the time of
day anywhere where is this going to say a
> ß right.
So now what else do we need yet we need to
define p right so for that what do we need
well if I am in state high what is the probability
I will go to state low okay forget about going
to out of battery that is what we needed for
the rewards but for the test state transition
so from high to low what is the probability
that will happen if I am actively seeking
again so that is basically what we need right
so I mean state hi I am actively seeking a
can what is the probability I will stay in
state high what is the probability will go
to state low.
Right so like that and likewise if I am in
state low and I am actively seeking a care
what is the probability I will stay in state
low what is the probability will go to state
high and I am in state low and I am waiting
for can what is the probability I will stay
in state lower the probability will go to
state high right and so on so forth so these
are all the things that you need for defining
the state transition probabilities of course
if I am in state high and I do action recharge
what we want?
Exactly.
So if I am in state low I do action recharged
with probability 1 I will go to state height
right so we will actually prohibit recharge
action instate Heidi well it does not make
sense I am already fully charged I do not
want to go plugging in again all right so
I will fill diesel of that all depends right
I could just have a stochastic policy I can
say that ok my policy is that if I'm in state
high with probability 0 point 8 I will search
with probability 0 point 2 I will just stay
so I mean so I am not talking about solutions
here.
I am just talking about defining the problem
this is what I was mentioning earlier also
do not do not get into how the solution will
look like right sometimes you will have to
think about how the solution will look like
because you need to know if you are giving
the state sufficient expressiveness so that
you know when the solution should change and
things like that but do not worry too much
about the structure of the solution.
So now we will just draw this some kind of
a state transition diagram.
.
Right so let us do the act state high first
so there are two actions from state high one
and one is actively seek cans right so active
so what are the possible outcomes of active
so what is the probability that I am going
to be in high know some values equal is also
possible well depends on how wide my high
band is rate and how much power my actor action
is going to consider I don't know this is
to say some numbers here right what is other
action I can take here right and what is the
something some numbers it has now is there
anything else I need to specify I need to
look at what the reward is going to be for
having done that right.
So what will be the robot here what yeah I
will get plus one for a can but the expected
number of cans I am going to collect this
a right there is a probability of me getting
a can so the expected reward will be a right
likewise here the expected what is going to
be so from low I again three actions no from
low I have three actions or to read a three
actions so what are the actions right so I
will do the easy one first right from low
if I do recharge with probability 1 I will
go to high and I will get 0 to 1 right.
So now come see more interesting suppose I
do wait here the rein chance that we will
go to hide I could write so it is also possible
but very low very low probability when I am
not doing anything so if I already set point
one here is the probability of discharging
I will say point 1 minus and I would still
get a can write and this one is
likewise if I am actively seeking the set
mixes some small probability I met not discharged
and they will keep accruing rewards at a right
but then I might actually discharged with
a high probability and then I go to the high
state and I also get the additional minus
3 along the way.
I mean whether you do this + ß + a or not
is again a choice right you can say that as
if I run out nobody is actually going to give
me a can right so people might snatch away
they can I already have I do not know what
you can choose whatever I mean this is again
a choice I just I just chose to add the a
and ß here we can just not do but you can
you get the sense of what we are doing here
right so is a very simple problem it took
us a while to identify all the factors right
and we chose to ignore a whole bunch of factors
because you identified a lot of useful factors
right we chose to ignore a whole bunch of
factors or in order to come up with a simple
tractable MDP right okay.